Inventory of the Henriette B. Von Blon papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Henriette B. Von Blon papers
1940-1952
52011
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Letters received from Japanese Americans interned first at the Pomona Assembly Center in California and later at the Heart Mountain Relocation Center (Wyoming) during World War II relating to conditions in the camps; and clippings from American newspapers relating to French culture and the military defeat of France in 1940.
Von Blon, Henriette B.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1952.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Henriette Von Blon lived in Los Angeles, California, with her husband, John L. Von Blon, and her two children, Phillip and Marie Adele. John L. Von Blon was an editor at the Los Angeles Times for seventeen years. Henriette also contributed to publications, like the popular art magazine The International Studio.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Henriette B. Von Blon papers contain personal materials, correspondence, illustrations, and a photograph, with an overarching emphasis on Henriette Von Blon and her family's relationship with an interned Japanese American family who had been the Von Blons' neighbors and friends. The head of that family, Taketaro Azeka, was a barber by trade who also practiced poetry and art. The Von Blons stored the belongings that Azeka and his daughters’ families could not bring with them to relocation centers during World War II. Mrs. Von Blon also acted as a character reference for Azeka’s daughter, Shizuko Horiuchi.
Correspondence from Azeka and his three daughters cover the family’s time at both the Pomona Assembly Center in California and the Heart Mountain Relocation Center in Wyoming during World War II. Letters received by the Von Blon family from 1942 to 1944 describe life in the internment camps and gratitude for the Von Blons' support during the family’s time in the camps. Illustrations by Azeka sent with these letters depict both the Pomona Assembly Center and the Heart Mountain Relocation Center and the daily life of detainees.
In addition to this material, the collection includes a scrapbook of newspaper clippings compiled by Von Blon for her daughter, Marie Adele, relating to conditions in France during World War II from 1940 to 1941.
Heart Mountain Relocation Center (Wyo.).; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Materials relating to Japanese American internees at Pomona Assembly Center and Heart Mountain Relocation Camp, 1942-1952
  - Correspondence, 1942-1952
    - Azeka, Taketaro, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes illustrations.
    - Azeka, Miyeko, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Gotanda, Umeko, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Horiuchi, Shizuko, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      Includes photograph.
    - Von Blon, Henriette B., 1952 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - War Relocation Authority, 1943 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Illustrations of internment camps by Taketaro Azeka, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Scrapbook containing articles and clippings relating to conditions in France during World War II, 1940-1941 (Box 1)